Now that we have our main scene saved
Main シーンの保存が終わりました
let's create our game board, or play field.
ゲームボード、またはプレイフィールドを作ってみましょう
To do this we'll need to add in our
まず、Background (背景) という
first sprite, called Background.
最初のスプライトを設定します
We can do this by navigating to the folder Sprites
アセットインポートしたときに取得した
which was imported when we imported our assets.
Sprites フォルダーを選びます
In Sprites we'll see a sprite named Background.
その中に　Background というアセットがあります
Drag Background from the project view
Project ビューから Background をドラッグして
in to the hierarchy.
Hierarchy ビューにドロップします
This will create a new game object
これでBackground という
called Background.
新しいゲームオブジェクトができました
This new game object is created
この新しいゲームオブジェクトは
with a sprite renderer
Sprite Renderer コンポーネントが
component attached.
アタッチされた状態で作成されます
Game objects are the entities
Unity 内部でシーンを創造している
which scenes are made out of in Unity.
実体がオブジェクトです
Each piece of a game scene,
ゲームシーンの各ピースは
whether it's the player, a wall in the level,
それがプレイヤー、フロアを分ける壁、コイン、なんであれ
or a coin can be it's own game object.
それぞれがゲームオブジェクトなのです
All game objects are created
すべてのゲームオブジェクトは
with a transform component attached.
Transform コンポーネント付きで作成されます
The transform component is used to
Transform コンポーネントは
store and manipulate the position,
オブジェクトの位置、回転、スケールの
rotation and scale of the object.
保存と操作に使われます
To add additional functionality to
他の機能を
the game object we can add
ゲームオブジェクトに追加するには
additional components.
コンポーネントを追加します
Adding a component allows a game
コンポーネントを加えると
object to do something.
ゲームオブジェクトに何かをさせることができます
For example adding an audio
例えば ゲームオブジェクトに
source component to a game object
オーディオソースコンポーネントを加えると
allows it to play sound.
サウンドを再生できます
The sprite renderer component
Sprite Renderer コンポーネントを加えると
allows a game object to display
ゲームオブジェクトは
a 2D image,
Sprite フィールドにある
shown in it's Sprite Field.
2D 画像を表示できるようになります
Dragging a sprite in to the scene
スプライトを Scene や Hierarchy へドラッグ& ドロップすると
or hierarchy is a shortcut provided by Unity.
これを手早く行うことができます
Since we can't have a sprite in the
ゲームオブジェクトにアタッチしていないスプライトを
scene that's not attached to a game object
シーンで使用できないので
Unity creates a game object
Unity は適切な Sprite Rendererが
with the appropriate sprite renderer attached
アタッチされた状態でゲームオブジェクトを作成し
and automatically references the
ドラッグされたスプライトアセットが表示されるように
dragged sprite asset to be displayed.
自動的に参照します
Because we drag the sprite in to the
スプライトを Hierarchy ウィンドウに
hierarchy window it
ドラッグするので
should appear at origin,
このスプライトは基本位置
or the position (0, 0, 0) in our world.
つまり ワールドの (0, 0, 0) の位置に表示されます
To make sure the sprite is at origin
このスプライトが基本位置にあるように 念のため
reset the transform component
Transform コンポーネントをリセットします
using the context sensitive gear menu
Transform コンポーネントの右上にある
in the upper-right of the transform component.
歯車型メニューで行います
This will reset the position of the game
こうすることによって もしオブジェクトの位置が
object to the coordinates (0, 0, 0)
シーンの座標の (0, 0, 0) でない場合に
in our scene if it's not already there.
リセットすることができます
The origin point of the world
ワールドの基本位置は
is where all of the coordinates
シーンのすべての座標が
in the scene are calculated from.
算出される基本となる位置です
Currently we can only see part
現在 Scene ビューの
of the background in the scene view.
Background の一部しか見えていません
With the game object still selected
そのゲームオブジェクトにフォーカスがあるときに
move the cursor over the scene view
カーソルを Scene ビューに移動して
and type the F key.
F キーを押します
This allows us to see the entire
こうするとゲームオブジェクトの全体を
game object in the scene view.
Scene ビューで見ることができます
You can also choose Frame Selected
Edit メニューからFrame Selected を
from the Edit menu.
選んでも同じです
Looking at our current scene we can
現在のシーンを見てみると
see grid lines which provide
グリッドラインがあり
a reference for spacing in the scene.
シーン内で空間を調整するときの基準になります
For the purposes of this project
このプロジェクトの目的上
we'll turn these off.
グリッドラインをオフにします
Select the Gizmos menu
Scene ビューで Gizmos メニューを選び
in the scene view and deselect Show Grid.
Show Grid が選択してあるチェックをはずします
Now let's create our Player object.
では プレイヤーオブジェクトを作りましょう
In this assignment our player will
この課題では プレイヤーは
be represented by our UFO sprite.
UFO スプライトで表現されます
Drag the UFO sprite
UFO スプライトを Hierarchy に
in to the hierarchy.
ドラッグしてください
A game object called UFO
UFO というゲームオブジェクトが
will be created with an
Sprite Renderer コンポーネント付きで
attached sprite renderer component
作成され
to display the sprite we dragged in.
ドラッグしたスプライトを表示します
Let's rename our newly created
新しく作ったゲームオブジェクトの名を
game object from UFO to Player.
UFO から Player に変更しましょう
With the UFO highlighted
UFO にハイライトがある状態で
navigate to the inspector
Inspector に移動して
and click in the text field at the top.
一番上のテキストフィールドをクリックします
With the text highlighted type Player.
文字がハイライトされている状態で Player と入力します
Now we have two sprites in our game.
これで このゲームにスプライトが2 つになりました
Because sprites are not 3D objects
スプライトは 3D オブジェクトではないので
we need to manually determine
どのスプライトを
which sprites will be
他のスプライトの上 (つまり 前面) に
rendered on top or
レンダリングするかを
in front of one another.
手動で決定する必要があります
The way we do this is by assigning
これを行うには
each of our sprites to a sorting layer.
それぞれのスプライトを Sorting Layer (ソートの層) に割り当てます
If we click on the Sorting Layer drop down
Sprite Renderer コンポーネントのSorting Layer の
in our sprite renderer component
ドロップダウンをクリックします
we can see that there are
すると プロジェクトに
four sorting layers already
すでに 4 つの Sorting Layer が
defined in our project.
用意されています
These are Default,
これらは Default、
Background, Pickups and Player.
Background、Pickups、Player です
These sorting layers are part of
これらのSorting Layerは
the project settings.
プロジェクト設定の一部です
They were imported when we chose to
以前、アセットパッケージをインポートするときに
import our asset package as a complete project
プロジェクトを全体を選んだので
in episode one.
そのときに設定もインポートされました
To add your own sorting layers
独自の Sorting Layer を追加するには
select Add Sorting Layer
Add Sorting Layer　を選び
and then click the + button.
+ ボタンを押します
Sorting layers can be reordered
クリックしてドラッグすると
by clicking and dragging.
Sorting Layer の順序を変えられます
We already have all the sorting layers
必要なレイヤーはすべてあるので
we need so we can delete
たったいま作った新しいレイヤーを
this one we have just created
削除します
by highlighting it and clicking the - button.
レイヤーを選んで – (マイナス) ボタンをクリックします
The order of the layers here is important.
ここでのレイヤーの順番は重要です
Layers are rendered in
レイヤーはリストの上から下の順に
list order from top to bottom.
レンダリングされます
With the bottom layer being rendered
リストの 1 番下のレイヤーが
last and therefore
最後にレンダリングされます
appearing in front of
そのため、その前にレンダリングされたレイヤーの
the previous layers.
前面に表示されます
This means that objects in
つまり、
the Background sorting layer will be
Background レイヤーは
rendered on top of objects in Default
Default レイヤーのオブジェクトの上にレンダリングされます
and that objects in Pickups
Pickups レイヤーのオブジェクトは
will be rendered on top
レンダリングされ
of objects in Background, and so on.
Background レイヤーのオブジェクトに重ねられます
For this project we will use
このプロジェクトでは
the layers and their order
レイヤーとその順序は
as defined in the project settings.
プロジェクト設定で決められたままで使用します
Highlight the Background object.
Background オブジェクトを選択します
In it's sprite renderer component
Sprite Renderer コンポーネントで
set the sorting layer to Background.
Sorting レイヤーを Background に設定します
Then highlight the Player object to Player.
それから Player オブジェクトを選択し
and set it's sorting layer.
Sorting レイヤーを Player に設定します
Next we want to adjust the
次に Player のスケールを
scale of our Player.
調整します
We can do this in a number of ways.
何通りものやり方があります
One way is to use the Scale tool.
1 つめはScale ツールを使う方法です
With the tool selected simply grab the
Scale ツールを選択して 調整したいアクセスハンドルをつまみ
access handle we want to change and drag
ハンドルをドラッグして
the handle rescaling the Player.
Player のスケールを変更します
We can also click and drag on the
変更したいフィールドのタイトルを
title of the fields we want to change.
クリック、ドラッグする方法もあります
Or we can type a number directly
また、変更したいフィールドに
in to the fields we want to change.
直接数字を入力することも可能です
We can tab between fields
タブでフィールドを移動し
and hit enter or return to
Enter/Return キーで
confirm our choice.
変更した値を確定します
Let's use 0.75 for the X
X フィールドに 0.75
and Y fields to scale the Player to 75%
Y フィールドに 0.75 を入力して
of it's original size.
Player を元のサイズの 75% に縮小します
Note that because we're working
気をつけたいのは、
in 2D space changing the
今は 2D スペースで作業しているので
scale value for the Z axis
Z 軸の値を変えても
will have no effect.
何も影響がありません
We can think of each sprite as a
それぞれのスプライトは
pane of glass with an image painted on it.
画像が描かれている 1 枚の窓ガラスのようなものです
It's flat without depth or volume.
深さや容量がない平面です
You may have noticed that if we change either the
すでに気づいているかもしれませんが
X or Y scale values to
X や Y のスケール値を
negative numbers the image
負の数に変えると
will be reversed along the horizontal
それぞれ、水平または垂直の座標方向に
or vertical axis respectively.
画像が反転されます
So far we've been working in the scene view,
ここまで Scene ビューで作業してきました
which you can think of as our work area.
それは、作業場のようなものと考えてよいでしょう
If we click over to the game view
Game ビューをクリックすると
we can see what our player will
ゲームをプレイするときに プレイヤーが
actually see when they're playing the game.
実際に見る光景が見えます
Notice when we switch to the game view
Game ビューに切り替えると
our view is much tighter on
ビューがかなりいっぱいで
the player and we can't see the whole background.
背景全体をみることができません
In the case of the game that we're trying to design
私たちが作ろうとしているゲームの場合
this is going to make it pretty difficult to play
この状態でゲームをプレイするのは極めて難しいため
so what we're going to do is we're going to
どうするかというと
adjust the view of the camera
カメラのビューを調整します
so that it can see more of the board.
すると、ボードのすべてが見られます
Let's start by highlighting
まず Main Camera を選択するところから
the main camera.
スタートしましょう
With the main camera highlighted we'll
Main Camera を選択すると
see that it's also a game object with
それもまた、ヘッダーと Transform をもつ
a header and transform
ゲームオブジェクトですが
but it has a camera component attached.
camera コンポーネントがアタッチされています
When we created this project we
このプロジェクトを作ったとき
set the project type to 2D.
プロジェクトタイプを 2D に設定しました
With a 2D project all new
2D プロジェクトでは、すべての新規のカメラは
cameras will use orthographic projection
Orthographic Projection (平行投影) を使用してシーンをレンダリングします
Using orthographic projection
Orthographic Projection (平行投影) を使用するということは
means that objects will not appear
オブジェクト表示の大きさは
larger or smaller based on
カメラとの距離が変わっても
their distance from the camera.
変化しないということです
To visualise how this works
実際にどうなるかを見るために
let's temporarily exit 2D mode.
一時的に 2D モードを終了します
In the scene view we can see
Scene ビューで
our camera and our sprites.
カメラとスプライトが見えます
We can rotate the view by
シーン内で Alt/Option キーを押しながらドラッグして
alt or option + dragging in the scene.
ビューを回転できます
If we highlight the camera game object
Camera ゲームオブジェクトを選ぶと
we can see the camera's frustum.
Camera の錐台が見えます
The frustum is the camera's viewable area.
この錐台が camera の可視範囲です
If we briefly change our
少しの間だけ Camera の Projection を
camera's projection to perspective
Perspective (透視投影) に変えてみましょう
we can see that the shape of the
錐台の形が変わり
frustum changes and
同様に
so does our view of the scene.
シーンのビューも変化します
If we temporarily move our
Player ゲームオブジェクトを
Player game object towards
Z 軸に沿って
the camera along the Z axis
カメラの方に移動すると
we will see that it's size
Player ゲームオブジェクトのサイズが
grows larger in the camera preview.
Camera Preview で大きくなります
If we switch back to orthographic
Projection を Orthographic （平行投影） に戻すと
projection however we can see that
透視投影とは異なり
although the object is
オブジェクトが
closer to the camera
カメラに近いにもかかわらず
it does not appear larger in the frame.
フレーム内で大きくは表示されていません
Let's reset the Player's position to (0, 0, 0)
Player の位置を (0, 0, 0) にリセットし
and make sure the camera is using orthographic projection
カメラの Projection がOrthographic (平行投影) であることを確かめ
before we return the scene view
Scene ビューを
to 2D mode.
2D モードに戻します
Next let's get a better view
さて、camera のプレイフィールドを
of our play field for our camera.
もう少し見やすくしましょう
Click on the game view.
Game ビューをクリックしてください
To change how much is visible to
平行投影のcameraの
an orthographic camera we
可視範囲を変更するために
adjust it's Size field.
Size フィールドを調整します
Let's click on the Size property
Camera の Size をクリックして
of our camera and drag.
ドラッグします
By dragging we can find that a value
ドラッグして 16.5 あたりが
of around 16.5 works nicely.
ちょうどよい具合だということがわかります
Now we can see that the Player
Player が
is at the centre of the board,
ボードの中央に配置され
and the board is sitting on a blue background.
ボードは青い背景上におかれています
This blue background is the default
2D モードで作業する場合
for new scenes when working in 2D mode.
この青い背景は新規シーンのデフォルトです
Let's change this to something better
この背景をもう少しこのゲームに合ったものに
suited to our game.
変えてみましょう
We can see that the camera has a
Camera には Background という
property called Background.
プロパティーがあります
This allows us to select the background colour.
これで背景色を選べます
Click on the colour swatch to open
カラースォッチをクリックして
the colour picker.
カラーピッカーを開きます
To choose a colour we can click and drag
色を選ぶには、色をクリックしてからドラッグするか
or enter a value numerically.
数値を入力します
Let's use numeric values to set
数値を使って
the background colour.
背景色を設定してみましょう
For the colours red, green and blue
色の原色の R (赤)、G (緑)、B (青) に
let's use the values 32, 32, 32.
それぞれ 32 を入力します
This will give us a nice dark grey background colour.
これで丁度良い暗灰色の背景色になりました
Congratulations, we now have a
よくできました
Player game object and a background play field.
Player ゲームオブジェクトと Background のプレイフィールドが出来上がりました
In the next lesson we'll learn how to add
次回は
a script to our Player
Player にスクリプトを設定して
to enable them to move around the playing field
2D の物理演算を利用して
using 2D physics.
プレイフィールドで Player をあちこちに移動させることを学びます